Guide to the Seaman Family Papers 1761-1983 (bulk 1830-1923) MS 552
New-York Historical Society
Seaman Family Papers
1761-1983 (bulk 1830-1923)
New-York Historical Society
MS 552
6 Linear feet (6 boxes)
The Seaman Family Papers consist of the personal, business and legal papers of four related families based in Long Island and Dutchess County, New York. The Van Horns and Freemans were united with the Seamans and DeWindts by the marriage of Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman and George Williams Seaman in 1903.
Provenance
Donation, Patricia Seaman Daniels, daughter of Irmingarde Freeman Seaman, 1990
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Biographical Note
Missing Title
November 11, 1868 Birth of George Williams Seaman Member of an old Dutchess County family and descendant of President John Adams. Worked in general exports at the David Brown Company in New York City, later George W. Seaman, Inc. (Obituary: New York Times 1/29/1942)
April 2, 1878 Birth of Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman Worked as an interior decorator in New York City and East Hampton, Long Island, prior to her marriage. Unlike most immediate family members, used an older spelling of Van Horne with an "e."
June 9, 1903 Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman and George Williams Seaman marry. At the time of the wedding, George is referred to as "superintendent of the Reformed Sunday School and a well-known young society man."
1921 Retirement of George Williams Seaman
January, 1942 Death of George Williams Seaman
August, 1968 Death of Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman Seaman
The marriage of Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman and George Williams Seaman joined together four Dutchess County, New York, families -- Van Horn, Freeman, DeWindt and Seaman. The following are family members mentioned within the collection and the relationship of each to Irmingarde or George W. Seaman. (Note: "DeWindt" is sometimes seen within the collection as "DeWint.")
Missing Title
Abner O. Van Horn (b.1814; d.1885) Maternal Grandfather of Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman Seaman. New York City businessman, inventor and owner of Abner Van Horn and Company, "machinists and brass founders, and manufacturers and dealers in wrought iron pipe and fittings of all kinds" (from letterhead). Died of cholera in 1885. (Obituary: Patchogue Advance 9/19/1885)
Abner Van Horn, M.D. (b.1845; d.1917) Uncle of Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman Seaman
Henry Voorhees Freeman (b.1829; d.1888) Father of Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman Seaman
Ida Van Horn Freeman (b. 1840; d.1898) Mother of Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman Seaman
Genevieve Freeman Sister of Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman Seaman
Gertrude Van Horn (b. 1849; d. 1922) Aunt of Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman Seaman
Gay Van Horn Aunt of Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman Seaman
Sadie Van Horn (b. 1847; d. 1926) Aunt of Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman Seaman
Alice Van Horn (b. 1853; d. 1926) Aunt of Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman Seaman
Gidney Underhill Uncle of Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman Seaman (Married Irmingarde's father's sister, Josephine.)
Romietta Q. O'Dowd Niece of Henry V. and Ida Van Horn Freeman (Daughter of Irmingarde's father's sister, Henrietta.)
May E. O'Dowd Niece of Henry V. and Ida Van Horn Freeman (Daughter of Irmingarde's father's sister, Henrietta.)
John Peter DeWindt (b. 1786; d. 1870) Grandfather of George Williams Seaman
Caroline Amelia Smith DeWindt (b. 1795; d.1852) Grandmother of George Williams Seaman. Caroline Amelia was a granddaughter of President John Adams.
George Allen Seaman Father of George Williams Seaman
Mary Catherine DeWindt Seaman (b. 1838; d. 1881) Mother of George Williams Seaman
Emily DeWindt Seaman (b. 1865; d. 1931) Sister of George Williams Seaman
Charles Henry "Carl" Seaman Brother of George Williams Seaman
Mary Groebe DeWindt Ketchum Sister of George Williams Seaman
John B. Seaman Uncle of George Williams Seaman
Amelia Seaman Aunt of George Williams Seaman. Wife of John B. Seaman.
Will Seaman Uncle of George Williams Seaman
Sophie Seaman Aunt of George Williams Seaman. Wife of Will Seaman.
Will, Lizzie and George Seaman Cousins of George Williams Seaman Children of Will and Sophie Seaman
Elizabeth Seaman Field Aunt of George Williams Seaman
Seaman Field Cousin of George Williams Seaman Son of Elizabeth Seaman Field
Julia DeWindt Van Wagenen Maternal Aunt of George Williams Seaman
Elizabeth DeWindt Cranch Maternal Aunt of George Williams Seaman
Louisa DeWindt Cook Maternal Aunt of George Williams Seaman
Isabella Adams DeWindt Furman Maternal Aunt of George Williams Seaman
Emily DeWindt Withers Maternal Aunt of George Williams Seaman
Caroline Elizabeth DeWindt Monell Maternal Aunt of George Williams Seaman. Caroline Elizabeth, oldest child of Caroline Amelia Smith and John Peter DeWindt, married Andrew Jackson Downing, considered by many to be the first great American landscaper. He, along with his mother-in-law, drowned in a steamboat disaster in the Hudson River in 1852. Caroline later married Judge John James Monell.
Scope and Content Note
An accumulation of personal and professional papers involving four related families on Long Island and in the Hudson Valley, this collection describes social life and customs as well as the structure and activities of several family businesses. Most of the items are dated between the 1830's and 1923 although there are some older legal documents (1761-1836) and a few items from mid and later twentieth century (1959, 1970, 1983).
The families represented in this collection were joined in 1903 with the marriage of Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman (granddaughter of Abner Van Horn) and George Williams Seaman (grandson of John Peter DeWindt and Caroline Amelia Smith).
Among the various items are personal correspondence among family members and with others; school documents and papers; military documents; legal documents including wills, patent documents; deeds, mortgages and leases; business correspondence, account books, receipts and other financial papers; photographs; newspaper clippings; essays and poetry; and many personal items such as the wedding book of Irmingarde and George Williams Seaman. Much of the material, especially that contained in the bound volumes, is related to business and finances, with the majority being Abner Van Horn's. The Seaman business material, however, is more descriptive of the history of the company (David Brown Company, George W. Seaman, Inc.).
The bound volumes are in relatively good condition although many of the covers are deteriorating and, in some of them, the ink has become faded. Several have been placed in boxes or enclosures. The correspondence and other papers are in good condition with some exceptions, noted in the Series Descriptions.
Arrangement
Correspondence is arranged by family -- Freeman / Van Horn and DeWindt / Seaman -- and, within family, by individual. Within individual, arrangement is chronological. Some letters are not identifiable as to sender or recipient. They are kept together, at the end of each family group. See Series Descriptions for arrangement of other types of papers.
This collection is organized into the following eight series:
Missing Title
Series I. Freeman/Van Horn Family Correspondence, 1836-1916, undated
Series II. Seaman/DeWindt Family Correspondence, 1815-1916, undated
Series III. School Documents and Papers, 1848-1893, undated
Series IV. Military Documents, 1816-1846
Series V. Legal Documents, 1761-1894, undated
Series VI. Business and Financial Documents, 1813-1923
Series VII. Personal Papers and Miscellany, 1805-1983, undated
Series VIII. Printed Matter and Photograph, 1858-1970, undated
Families -- New York (State); New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 19th century.; Inventors -- United States.; Merchants.
- Series I. Freeman/Van Horn Family Correspondence, 1836-1916
  Scope and Contents note
  The bulk of the correspondence in this series is that of Henry V. Freeman, his wife, Ida Van Horn Freeman, and their daughters, Genevieve and Irmingarde, and is related to personal matters. Other correspondence is from Ida Van Horn Freeman's sisters and other family members including Abner Van Horn, Ida Freeman's father.
  Henry Freeman wrote to his wife and daughters at home in Greenpoint, Long Island, while he was on business trips to Central America and California. After Henry's death in 1888, Ida returned to her family's home at Artist's Lake in Fishkill-on-Hudson (later renamed Beacon). A number of her letters were written to her daughters while they were away at school. Ida's sisters, Gertrude, Gay, Sadie and Alice also wrote to Genevieve and Irmingarde reporting Ida's failing health.
  Irmingarde's correspondence begins when she was quite young and continues into the early years of her marriage, signed using various forms of her name and nicknames. Of interest is a letter written on the last night of the nineteenth century (January 31, 1899) to her sister, enclosing a pressed four-leaf clover (Box 1, Folder 6).
  Also of particular note are Genevieve's letters to her father describing her intentions to become a doctor (Box 1, Folder 4, October 14, 1884) and Ida's letter to Henry showing her support for Grover Cleveland and describing an appearance in Brooklyn of Cleveland and George B. McClellan (Box 1, Folder 3, October 11, 1884).
  Of the more than 107 letters and fragments, most are in good condition. A few are difficult to read because the ink has faded and some of the fragments (Box 1, Folder 10) are in poor condition.
  - Letters Received, Abner Van Horn, 1836-1873, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Henry V. Freeman, 1866-1886, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Ida L. Van Horn Freeman (Mrs. H.V.), 1861-1898, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters Sent, Genevieve Freeman, 1884-1903, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters Received, Genevieve Freeman, 1880-1903, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters Sent, A. Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman (Mrs. George W. Seaman), 1892-1916, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters Received, A. Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman (Mrs. George W. Seaman), 1897-1916, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters Sent, Gay Van Horn, 1885-1898, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Romietta Q. and May R. O'Dowd, 1874-1884 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters and Fragments, Gidney Underhill, 1879-1880, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Freeman Family Correspondence, 1858-1903 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II. Seaman/DeWindt Family Correspondence, 1815-1916, undated
  Of the more than 105 letters in this series, fifty-three are those of John B. Seaman and the majority of his correspondence is with Charles C. Peck, his business partner or agent. These letters deal primarily with business transactions. There are quite a number of condolence letters to John B. Seaman and his niece, Lizzie, on the death of his wife Amelia. There are other letters of a personal nature as well.
  A number of family members moved to Texas and several of the letters are from Bonham County where John B. Seaman and C.C. Peck sold land to a Howard L. Parmele for the establishment of a settlement. Of interest is a letter from John Seaman's nephew, Seaman Field, describing the 'new city' of Dallas and commenting on his suspicion and dislike for members of the Parmele family (Box 2, Folder 2 - March 15, 1874).
  Another letter of particular note was written to Emily Seaman on September 16, 1900, from "Lizzie" in Galveston, Texas (Box 2, Folder 4). The letter describes the devastating hurricane that killed thousands and destroyed much of the city. The letter is not in good condition, but it is legible.
  In Box 2, Folder 6, there is what appears to be a copy of a letter sent on November 5, 1815, from John Adams, the former U.S. President, to John P. DeWindt congratulating him on the birth of a daughter. The daughter, Caroline, was born on Adams' birthday.
  - Correspondence, George A. Seaman, 1845-1891 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters Received, John B. Seaman, 1859-1878 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Lizzie Seaman, 1867-1893 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Emily Seaman, 1876-1900 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, George Williams Seaman, 1886-1916, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Seaman-DeWindt Correspondence, 1815-1874 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series III. School Documents and Papers, 1848-1893, undated
  Several documents and papers related to school activities are included in the collection. Essays and lecture notes belonging to George A. Seaman are included in Box 2, Folder 7; Ida Van Horn Freeman's grammar school testimonials and a tuition receipt are in Box 2, folder 8. Two school notebooks in Box 2, Folder 9 contain the lecture notes of William Morrow Knox. A variety of subjects (e.g., physical geography, logic, English literature) are included.
  - School Papers, George A. Seaman, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - School Documents, Ida L. Van Horn Freeman, 1860 - 1893 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - School Notebooks, William Morrow Knox, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series IV. Military Documents, 1816-1846
  Abner Van Horn's military appointments -- as Infantry Ensign and as Infantry Lieutenant -- are included, as are Regimental Orders from Colonel Oran. W. Rogers -- one to serve as member of a Regimental Court Martial and one to organize parades. Box 2, Folder 10 includes the original documents as well as photostats of each.
  In Box 2, Folder 11, there is an 1816 document identifying Andrew Van Horne as a soldier in the Third Regiment Horse Artillery Company, New York State Artillery.
  - Military Documents, Abner Van Horn, 1842-1846 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Military Document, Andrew Van Horne, 1816 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series V. Legal Documents, 1761-1894, undated
  A variety of legal documents is included in this collection, arranged by family and, to the extent possible, by type of document within family. Box 3 contains items such as deeds, leases, wills, bonds, agreements, and a lengthy court transcript, belonging to members of the Van Horn and Freeman families, Abner Van Horn predominating. In Box 4, there are Seaman and DeWindt family legal documents including a copy of the will of John Peter DeWindt (Box 4, Folder 4). In Box 4, Folder 3, is a group of 37 deeds, wills, agreements, etc. involving certain families (e.g., Corwin, Howell, Woodhull, and DeWindt) from Southold, Riverhead and other Long Island towns, dating from 1761 to 1837. Among the documents are several relating to 'vessels' as well as many concerning real estate. There is also a copy of official minutes from a meeting (April 9, 1793) in which two ministers reached satisfaction "respecting the sentiments about gospel and ministerial order." Box 4, Folders 5 and 6 contain patent documents.
  - Van Horn Deeds & Leases, 1810-1894 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Van Horn Mortgages, 1837-1885 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Van Horn Bonds, 1834-1880 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Van Horn - Freeman Family Agreements, 1834-1883 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Van Horn - Freeman Family Wills, 1841-1893 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Abner Van Horn Court Transcript, 1860 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Abner Van Horn Miscellaneous Legal Documents, 1856-1874 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Henry V. Freeman Miscellaneous Legal Documents, 1860-1862 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Legal Documents Relating to Various Long Island Families, 1761-1837 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - DeWindt - Seaman Family Legal Documents, 1850-1882 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Van Horn Patent Documents, 1856-1884, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Campbell Morfit Letters Patent and Assignment Documents, 1858-1861 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series VI. Business and Financial Documents, 1813-1923
  This series (one box and 36 volumes) contains papers of a business or financial nature, the majority having belonged to Abner Van Horn. The folders are arranged by type of document with the exception of Box 5, Folder 1. This folder holds two packets of various document types all involving Junius Judson, manufacturer of governors and valves, who supplied valves to Van Horn's business. The packets include correspondence, receipts, accounts, illustrations, etc. Folders 3 and 4 contain a large number of receipts and bills. Along with these are what appear to be worksheets on which bills were calculated. The items include Van Horn business purchases as well as customer accounts and bills. They are arranged chronologically, falling between 1864 and 1879 with the bulk dated 1870. In Folder 5 are bonds issued by the Mott Manufacturing Company along with a notice that the Mott Company is filing bankruptcy (both Van Horn and Henry Freeman are listed as creditors); a related letter written by Abner Van Horn; and a document transferring company stock to Van Horn. Items in Folder 7 include miscellaneous documents such as a survey report, insurance policy documents and cancelled checks.
  Two folders contain Seaman Family items. Folder 8 contains an account book belonging to the George A. Seaman family. Among its entries are items purchased for his children, Emily, George and Charles (Carl). There are several of George Williams Seaman's receipts in Folder 9. The final folder (Folder 10) in this series is an account book fragment; the author is not identifiable.
  The majority of volumes in this series are those of Abner Van Horn and Company. According to the 1870 New York City Directory, the company was located at 624 5th Street, between Avenue D and Lewis Street. Most of the volumes are account books or ledgers. Among them are a Workmen's Account Book and a Wage Book that identify hours worked and wages paid. It appears that Henry V. Freeman, Van Horn's son-in-law, was also an employee of the company. A Diary (1880-1884) belonging to Henry V. Freeman is of interest not only for its financial content but also the information printed in the volume (e.g., "Eclipses for 1880," "Church Days," postage and interest tables, "The Interest Laws of the United States" and "Population of States and Territories 1870").
  A volume labeled "Journal" is actually used as both an account book and a scrapbook. Belonging to Abner Van Horn, it contains transactions that occurred in 1836-1839 while he was doing business in Charleston, South Carolina, as well as business conducted in 1842 in New York. The rest of the volume is taken up with newspaper clippings on a variety of topics, one of which is Shakespeare, primarily the controversy over who actually wrote Shakespeare's plays, etc. There are also articles on Epictetus, Raphael, Rubens, Swedenborg, Prior and others, as well as an article by Henry Ward Beecher called "Cats, Dogs and Robins."
  Two of the volumes belonged to Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman Seaman. One is an Account Book from her home furnishings and decorating business. The other, labeled "Bank Book," contains lists of layette items and their costs for two different years - 1904 and 1908. Her daughter, Sarah Corvinus, was born in 1904 and her son, Ogden Van Horne, in 1908.
  While fewer in number than the Van Horn volumes, those of the Seaman family contain a mix of business papers that reveal a good deal about the David Brown Company, later George W. Seaman, Inc., a New York City-based import-export business dealing in wood and rubber. Much of the material is loosely contained within a large Ledger Book (1913-1923) and a Letterbook (1918-1923) of business correspondence, shipping documents, bills of lading and brochures.
  Some of the volumes in this series are in good condition although others have begun to deteriorate, have faded ink, or have come unbound. The letterbook of business correspondence contains numerous items in poor condition. Several volumes are housed in boxes or enclosures (*).
  - Abner Van Horn Business Correspondence, Accounts, Receipts - Junius Judson Governor Works, 1861-1871 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Abner Van Horn Proposals and Related Documents, 1867-1877 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Abner Van Horn & Co. Receipts and Bills (1 of 2), 1864 - 1879 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Abner Van Horn & Co. Receipts and Bills (2 of 2), 1864-1879 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Abner Van Horn - Mott Manufacturing Co. Bonds, 1872 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Abner Van Horn Pages from Account Book, 1835 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Abner Van Horn Miscellaneous Business Documents, 1838-1870 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Seaman Family Account Book, 1876-1891 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - George W. Seaman Receipts, 1916, Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Account Book Fragment, 1821 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Receipt Book Samuel and Mary Freeman *, 1813-1840 (Volume Unknown container 581 for instance of Receipt Book Samuel and Mary Freeman *)
  - Journal A. Van Horn *, 1836-1875 (Volume Unknown container 582 for instance of Journal A. Van Horn *)
  - Account Book A. Van Horn *, 1847-1851 (Volume Unknown container 583 for instance of Account Book A. Van Horn *)
  - Account Book Van Horn *, 1847-1851 (Volume Unknown container 584 for instance of Account Book Van Horn *)
  - Day Book A. Van Horn, 1854-1867 (Volume Unknown container 585 for instance of Day Book A. Van Horn)
  - Account Book A. Van Horn, 1854-1869 (Volume Unknown container 586 for instance of Account Book A. Van Horn)
  - Accounts Receivable / Payable Abner Van Horn, 1857-1874 (Volume Unknown container 587 for instance of Accounts Receivable / Payable Abner Van Horn)
  - Ledger CM& J, 1859-1861 (Volume Unknown container 588 for instance of Ledger CM& J)
  - Ledger A & A Van Horn, 1861-1881 (Volume Unknown container 589 for instance of Ledger A & A Van Horn)
  - Account Book Van Horn / Freeman, 1861-1884 (Volume Unknown container 590 for instance of Account Book Van Horn / Freeman)
  - Stock Book NY OLEIC Company (Van Horn), 1861-1884 (Volume Unknown container 591 for instance of Stock Book NY OLEIC Company (Van Horn))
  - Bank Book (Check Register) A. Van Horn *, 1862-1875 (Volume Unknown container 592 for instance of Bank Book (Check Register) A. Van Horn *)
  - Account Book, 1864-1865 (Volume Unknown container 593 for instance of Account Book)
  - Account Book, 1865-1866 (Volume Unknown container 594 for instance of Account Book)
  - Ledger, 1865-1866 (Volume Unknown container 595 for instance of Ledger)
  - Account Book A. Van Horn & Co., 1866-1870 (Volume Unknown container 596 for instance of Account Book A. Van Horn & Co.)
  - Ledger, 1866-1872 (Volume Unknown container 597 for instance of Ledger)
  - Workmen's Account Book Van Horn, 1866-1873, 1877-1883 (Volume Unknown container 598 for instance of Workmen's Account Book Van Horn)
  - Account Book, 1868-1871 (Volume Unknown container 599 for instance of Account Book)
  - Account Book, 1868-1875 (Volume Unknown container 600 for instance of Account Book)
  - Bank Book A. Van Horn *, 1868-1879 (Volume Unknown container 601 for instance of Bank Book A. Van Horn *)
  - Account Book, 1869-1870 (Volume Unknown container 602 for instance of Account Book)
  - Wage Book Freeman / Van Horn *, 1870-1872 (Volume Unknown container 603 for instance of Wage Book Freeman / Van Horn *)
  - Letterbook Abner Van Horn, 1870-1879 (Volume Unknown container 604 for instance of Letterbook Abner Van Horn)
  - Cash Book NY OLEIC Company (A. Van Horn), 1877-1878 (Volume Unknown container 605 for instance of Cash Book NY OLEIC Company (A. Van Horn))
  - Diary Henry V. Freeman *, 1880-1884 (Volume Unknown container 606 for instance of Diary Henry V. Freeman *)
  - Account Book Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman House Furnishing and Decorations *, 1902-1903 (Volume Unknown container 607 for instance of Account Book Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman House Furnishing and Decorations *)
  - Bank Book (Lists Layette Items and Costs ) Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman Seaman *, 1904, 1908 (Volume Unknown container 608 for instance of Bank Book (Lists Layette Items and Costs ) Irmingarde Van Horne Freeman Seaman *)